[Music]
healthy 7th Day Adventist vegetarians
maybe longest living but might that come
at a cost a seaman analysis at a
fertility clinic in lomalinda California
home to a large population of Adventists
raised questions about their sperm
quality though still within the normal
range vegetarians had about a 25% lower
sperm count and the few vegans tested
also had a lower sperm concentration but
they made up for that with their 30%
greater ajaculate volume the vegans did
have significally fewer activated sperm
though which is a sign of decreased
fertility the researchers suggested soy
consumption as a possible mechanism as
Adventist vegetarians in California
average about a half serving a day of
plant-based Meats many of which contain
soy soy phytoestrin have been put to the
test though and months of consuming up
to the equivalent of nearly 20 servings
of soy a day did not result in any
adverse effects on sperm parameters
there were only five vegans in the study
so the sperm quality findings could just
be a fluke but if verified this could
reflect an evolutionary tradeoff between
fertility and lifespan first proposed
nearly a century ago using a finely
tuned laser it's possible to selectively
destroy individual sell cells as the
tiny roundworm sea Elegance develops and
terminating the cells that give rise to
sperm and eggs significantly extends
lifespan the same phenomena can be
demonstrated in fruit flies potentially
Shifting the body's priorities from
reproduction to
survival the fertility versus longevity
tradeoff may be one of the reasons why
spaying and neutering our pets can
extend their lives based on a study of
mill millions of dogss and cats
sterilized dogs live about 20% longer
than intact dogs and Spade cats live
about 40% longer and neutered cats are
remarkable 60% longer what about men
whove been castrated Unix seem to live
25% longer than non-castrated men up
until the 1950s in the United States the
so-called feeble-minded were
involuntarily sterilized by the state in
a Eugenics program upheld by none other
than Oliver Wendell Holmes who wrote for
the majority on the Supreme Court quote
Society can prevent those who are
manifestly unfit from continuing their
kind the principle that sustains
compulsory vaccination is Broad enough
to cover cutting the Fallopian tubes
unquote the heinous practice of
compulsory sterilization did allow for a
natural experiment though and one mental
institution found that castrated men
lived about 14 years longer than intact
men in the same Hospital a genealogy
database of nearly 200,000 men and women
across three centuries in 16 countries
found that those who had fewer children
seemed to live longer centenarians for
example were found to have fewer
children at later ages this is not to
suggest that having fewer children will
make you live longer but rather that
constitutional factors that enhance
human lifespan may come at the expense
of reduced reproductive potential
another example of the antagonistic
ploopy Theory I talked about before for
example selection for lifespan extension
in model organisms can lead to longer
lived animals but with reduced
reproductive capacity it makes intuitive
sense when you consider the context of
food scarcity in lean times it makes
sense to put off reproduction until the
return of more favorable conditions to
ensure long-term survival in the
infamous Minnesota starvation study that
used conscientious objectors as guinea
pigs during World War II the study
subjects rapidly lost their libidos
after their calorie intake was cut in
half as one of them put it I have no
more sexual feeling than a sick
oyster the same calorie restriction that
extends the lives of animals can also
cause a reduction in the number of
progyny if you read my book how not to
age you'll be familiar with the nutrient
sensing aging Pathways igf-1 mtor
ampk that create kind of a seesaw
between tissue acceleration and
reproduction on one side and tissue
preservation and Rejuvenation on the
other thankfully we can shift the weight
to a more optimal balance with diet the
later girls start their periods the
longer they tend to live each year later
associated with significantly lower risk
of dying from heart disease and stroke
plateauing out with the lowest overall
mortality among those who don't start
menstruating until age
15 isn't 15 a little late it didn't Ed
to be a century ago the age of first
menstration averaged as late as nearly
17 similarly the age of breast
development has dropped an average of
about 3 months per decade of the last
half century around the world down to 9
or 10 years old in the United States
necessitating a change in textbook
definitions of quote unquote premature
puberty earlier breast development
before age 10 verses 12 or 13 is
associated with as much as 23% greater
breast cancer risk later in life and
each year later a girl starts to
menstrate is linked to significantly
lower risk of cancers of the uterus
liver skin bladder colon lung and breast
thankfully the age of puberty is
something over which we have a degree of
control higher levels of igf-1 are
associated with earlier sexual maturity
so it's no surprise that girls eating
more animal protein experienced puberty
significantly earlier in effect not seen
with protein from Plants a metaanalysis
of 16 studies on diet and development
found that one's first period appears to
start earlier by two months for each
additional one gr per day of animal
protein intake in childhood uh so for
example at 7 years old girls consuming
more than 12 serving of meat a week had
75% greater odds of menstruating within
the next 5 years or so compared to girls
at that age eating less than four
servings a week and this relationship we
seen for both red meat and poultry
consumption igf-1 and other aging
Pathways may not fully explain these
findings however as persistent
pollutants that build up in me like DDT
have also been linked to precaution is
puberty
[Music]